a subscriber recently left this comment
on one of my videos do you think you can
do a tutorial on keys I'm really
struggling to understand that part of
music theory and it would be great if
you could help with that so what is a
key in music theory what does the key of
C mean or the key of e being in a key is
a really important concept to understand
when you're learning music if there's
any other concepts in music you find
confusing or perhaps a word or a phrase
you've heard and you're not sure what it
means and you want me to answer or
perhaps create a future video one then
please ask me in the comments below if
you're new here this channel is your
guide through developing all the
different skills and knowledge you need
to become a better piano player and
musician so if that's something you want
to do consider clicking the subscribe
button and the notification bar so you
don't miss out on anything you need to
learn so a key tells you what scale is
being used as the basis to create the
music there's really two parts to the
name which note to start the scale from
and then which type of scale to start
from that note for example the key of
c-major means you're using the notes
from the C major scale for that piece of
music when we use the phrase in the key
of we really mean either major or minor
which are two different types of scale
the most common two you're going to come
across there's 12 different notes on the
piano and you can start a major scale
from any of those twelve notes giving
you 12 different keys and you can start
a minor scale from any of those 12 as
well a scale is just a group of notes
that we can use to create music with
like a color palette you'd use to paint
a picture most of the time we don't just
use all 12 notes we have organized
groups of notes that we know work well
together so major and minor scales are
seven out of those twelve but not the
same seven and each has a specific
pattern or spacing between the notes
these different patterns give the scales
very different sounds like different
color palettes we could play with
they're made up of something we call
intervals which are the names for the
different sized gaps or spacings between
notes they're really the fundamental
building blocks for scales and harmony
and melody so after this I really
recommend watching this video to learn
all about intervals properly and how to
name them we use them to describe lots
of other things in music so they're
really helpful to learn
covered my knee yet but this major scale
video will explain exactly how to build
and understand the major scale pattern
using intervals so in the key of E major
means using the E major scale for the
music in the key of F minor means using
the F minor scale for the music but
sometimes people don't specify and they
just say in the key of D usually that
means they're talking about major and
that's the same when people talk about
chords as well it's just worth
mentioning too that there's actually
some common variations of the minor
scale they can also fluctuate mid-song
so in the key of something minor could
mean any one of these or a changing mix
you don't need to learn these straight
away it's just good to know that they
exist and that being in a minor key
could also mean that once you have your
key let's use G major as an example I
said you use the notes from that scale
to create the music that means that you
can create all your melodies and harmony
from the notes of that scale ignoring
the other notes that aren't in it so for
G major we start on G and that's all the
white notes
apart from F where we use F sharp
instead using F natural the white one
would mean that we're no longer
following the major scale pattern that
we started from G and it would sound
different so with those notes we can do
anything we want we'd go up and down
leap around create any pattern or play
whatever has been written for us to play
locking inside this group of notes
remember these notes also repeat up and
down the piano so you're not just
restricted to this octave here if you
create a bit of music in a major key
it's gonna have a signature major sound
to it likewise if you create a piece of
music in a minor key you'll have a
signature minor sound to it although
sometimes it can be a bit ambiguous but
I'll talk about that more later on just
quickly if you're finding this video
helpful could you please give the video
a like and let me know in the comments
as those things are really helpful for
channels so the first note of the scale
the note that the scale is named after
is really important in this case that's
G we often call it the root or the tonic
and when you're in the key of G we can
say that the note G is the tonal center
of the music what that really means is
that G will sound like home sound
resolved and sound at rest to our ears
ending on a G makes something sound
finished like this
that sounds complete whereas if I ended
on a different note it's gonna sound
like it's unfinished hanging on that
note sounds like it's unfinished and
it's leading our ears somewhere else so
when we say we're in the key of g-major
having it sound like it could finish on
the note G is a really important part of
what that means
I said harmony as well so that means all
your chords come from the notes of this
scale too if I play these triads these
chords with three notes in playing every
other note of the scale I can just move
that pattern up through the scale but
when I'm about to pass the F I need to
make sure I lock in the scale and use F
sharp and if I keep going every time one
of these notes is about to cross the F
make sure to hit F sharp so this chord
here for example is not in the key of G
major because it has a note in it that's
not in the g major scale we also number
these notes of the scale so a chord that
starts from the first note is called
chord one a chord that starts from the
third note is called three and that's
actually a really useful and important
thing to learn I'll cover that in depth
in another video soon but just like this
note G which is the first note of the
scale the root sounded final in the key
of G major so does chord number one
which in this case would be a G major
chord chord number one in a major key is
always a major chord so if I play a
chord progression and finish it on G it
will sound complete
now just because you're in the key of G
for a piece that doesn't mean that you
absolutely have to always stick inside
it all the time
the scale is a set organized group of
sounds but sometimes you want to
experiment with other flavors too if you
play something inside the key the word
for that is diatonic and if you go
outside that's called non diatonic you
can completely change keys mid-song you
can change key for a section and then
come back to where you started you can
just go out the key temporarily with a
passing chord that doesn't completely
fit the scale as long as it sounds good
there's no rules that you have to stick
in the scale going out the key can
sometimes just give us more creative
options a melody could go out the key
too sometimes to really make a change
but also sometimes to just add a bit of
tension a bit of extra flavor to make
things interesting as a passing note in
between the main notes of the scale
every major scale has what's called a
relative minor scale I'm gonna cover
this soon in another video so you can
understand it fully but the quick
version in relation to keys is that for
every major scale there's also a minor
scale that has exactly the same notes in
exactly the same order they just loop
around and round but now there's a new
starting note a different note out of
those seven that sounds like home the
best example to learn this is with C
major and a minor both scales are all
the white notes and no black keys which
makes it easier to visualize C major
runs from C to C where any C will sound
like home an a minor runs from a to a
where any a will sound like home
remember I said there's a few variations
of minor scales only one of them though
uses the exact same seven notes as the
relative major so that's the one I'm
talking about at the moment this one is
called the natural minor although once
you're in it then remember it can change
to one of the other ones either way
you'd still say I'm in the key of a
minor for example so these are the seven
notes of the C major scale and if I take
the top two off a and B and I just put
them at the beginning you can see is the
same notes just in a different order
now this note a is the start and we hear
everything else relative to this new
home note which has a big impact on the
sound so using some of these notes I can
make C sound like home
so that's in the key of C major or I can
make a sound like home then we're in the
key of a-minor
and the key of c-major the C major chord
would be the home chord in the key of a
minor the a minor chord would be the
home chord sometimes in a piece of music
it's really obvious where sounds like
home like the AE or the C in this
example but sometimes music can be a bit
more ambiguous and at points it may
sound more major and at other times it
may sound more minor so although they
are technically different keys in a way
it's kind of like they are the same key
just to let you know before one last
topic I have links down below in the
description for lots of other useful and
important beginner theory and practical
videos you should check out after this
and lastly then for readers we have key
signatures which tell you what key were
in by showing you how many and which
sharps or flats are in the scale when
you follow the notes going up and down
on the sheet music you're going up and
down but locking into that scale you're
meant to be using so back in G major if
you're on the note e and the music tells
you to go up a second to the next note
in the scale you're not going to go up
to the F you're going to go up to the
f-sharp because that's the next note in
the scale the key signature tells you to
change every F to F sharp so as I said
every major scale has what's called a
relative minor scale which contains the
same notes just starting at a different
point in the sequence that means that
when you see a key signature it could
actually be either the major or the
relative minor and you can't tell just
from looking at the key signature you
need more information from the score or
from listening to it but either way it
still gives you enough information to
play all the correct notes and then if
it changes to one of the other types of
minor scale you keep the same key
signature but you just put in extra
flats sharps on Naturals on each of the
individual notes that you're changing if
you're new to piano you'll probably get
something from this video next giving
you four reasons to learn scales knowing
what to focus on when practicing them
will help you get a lot more out of them
please leave a like and let me know in
the comments if you got something out
this video as that's really helpful and
subscribe for more content to help you
develop your piano playing thanks for
watching